Hi, and welcome to the channel. I'm
Audrey, and in this video, I'm going to
show you some of the brand new MIDI
features in Studio 2.0. If you're a
keyboard player, these features are
great because you can play synth parts
like basslines, [music]
chords, and leads on your songs. But,
even if you don't play, MIDI is still a
super powerful tool that lets you have
more control and put your own personal
spin on your songs. [music]
I'll get into all of this in the video,
but first of all, let's talk about what
MIDI is for anyone who doesn't know.
MIDI is essentially a digital language
that allows instruments [music] and
software to talk to each other. It sends
data about the notes and performance,
[music] rather than actual sound. So,
that means you can record a melody once,
and then freely change the instrument,
[music]
the pitch, the timing, or the tempo
afterwards. And that's really powerful
in the context of a generative DAW like
Suno [music] Studio.
I'm going to show you [music] how to
record MIDI straight into your song
using what I'm most comfortable with, my
external MIDI keyboard, which is
connected to my computer via USB. I'm
working on this track, and I want to add
some strings to it. First, I need to add
a new MIDI track, and I can do that by
either clicking add new track on the
bottom left, or pressing shift T, and
then M on my keyboard. Next, I need to
arm the track, which means I need to
tell Studio which track I want to record
on, and I'll do that by clicking on the
A button on this new MIDI track. Next, I
need to select what sound I want to use
to record the MIDI. So, I'm going to go
to the very bottom left and click
effects, and it's going to default with
this plugin called wavetable. Wavetable
comes in with a default synth sound. You
can shape your sound. There's also a
bunch of presets in here. I'm just going
to select big strings.
I like that. I think that's what we're
going to use. To stay organized, I'm
going to just rename this MIDI track by
clicking on these three dots, selecting
rename track,
I'll call it synth strings, and hitting
enter. And just so you know, if you
don't have a piano keyboard, you can
just use your computer's keyboard
instead. If you click command K on a Mac
or control K on a PC, it pulls up this
keyboard overlay where you can either
type to play sounds
or just use your mouse
to click on the notes. The keyboard
overlay also gives you access to other
cool features including the arpeggiator
and chord modes, which you can have fun
playing around with, but we will go into
a deep dive on that at a later video.
All right, I'm ready to record. I want
to add my strings into the chorus of a
song that I've been working on, which
currently sounds like this.
>> [music]
[music]
>> We're about ready to record. Right
before I do that, I can go to this top
bar if I want to toggle the metronome or
counting or pre-roll. There's another
video on our channel about recording
that dives a little more into detail
about those settings if you're
interested. I'm just going to select
where in the song I want to start
recording and then I can either click
the red record button or use the
shortcut shift R. Let's record and play.
>> [music]
>> All right, that was pretty good. I feel
pretty good about what I just recorded,
so I could just leave it as is in my
arrangement, but let me show you some
other really cool things you can do in
Studio with this MIDI.
My favorite [music] thing is that you
can use the magic of Studio to create
audio clips from the MIDI. So, I'm going
to select the MIDI I just recorded, make
sure that the playhead is at the
beginning of the region, and then I can
click on the chat bar icon or press
enter. The chat bar might be the coolest
new feature in Studio 2.0. We'll have
another video going into that, but
basically you can just chat with Studio
and tell it to do things for you. Cover
the MIDI as a grand piano sound on a new
track. And then I can press the plus
button and hit controls if I want to
adjust the audio influence. So I'm going
to turn the audio influence up in this
case. All right, let's hear what we've
got.
Okay.
That's nice.
That was awesome. I just had Studio
create a brand new audio from the MIDI
that I gave it. But we can also go in
the other direction and turn audio into
MIDI using the get MIDI tool. Let's take
the synth part in the second verse which
sounds like this.
So first I'm going to create a new MIDI
track just like we did before. Now I'm
just going to select that part of the
synth that I want to convert to MIDI. So
I'll put the play head where I want to
make the first cut. Control click split.
Do the same for the ending point. And
I'm just dragging this section of synth
that I want down from the synth track
onto the MIDI track and then I just hit
convert to MIDI. It's literally that
simple. All right, let's hear what it
sounds like now.
>> [music]
>> Oh.
>> [singing]
>> That's a vibe.
>> [music]
>> Yeah.
That worked pretty well. It took my
audio and turned it into MIDI and from
here I can now edit the MIDI, change the
notes, change the timing, and I can also
export it to another DAW if I want to
use my own instruments. One of the
coolest things about Studio 2.0 is the
chat bar which lets you prompt new
tracks, lyrics, vocals, generate new
plugins from scratch, and yes, even
generate MIDI parts. All right, I'm
going to open up the chat bar and I'm
going to just say create a powerful
bassline part with MIDI that follows my
track.
And click enter. All right, we have a
MIDI back from our chat bar. It created
a bassline. Let's get a bass instrument.
I'm going to choose the preset sub.
Let's listen back.
>> [music]
[music]
>> That's great. I love that actually.
Okay, so I've just shown you how to
record MIDI and how to create MIDI using
the chat bar. And to remind you, MIDI
captures information not actual audio.
So I can go into the MIDI parts and
change some things around.
I'm going to double click to open up the
MIDI I recorded so I can see all of the
notes I played in here. I can delete any
notes I don't want. I can move notes up
and down to change the pitch. I can move
them side to side to change the timing.
Now when I move these notes around the
default view is chromatic meaning I can
move the notes anywhere, but that can
cause some problems if you move the
notes outside of the scale you're
working in. So a pro tip is select the
key that your song is in and then set
scale mode to on and then when you move
your notes around it's going to stay
within the key that your song is in. I
can change the timing of my notes by
moving the MIDI notes left to right, but
I can tighten the timing of my whole
MIDI performance using quantize. So I'm
going to select all of my notes and then
I'm going to go to this quantize button
and I can select whatever timing I want
here. I'm going to do eighth notes and
it just snaps all the notes right into
place. The last thing I'm going to cover
is velocity, pitch bend, and modulation.
So let's click on the bottom right
corner on the word automation. You can
think of velocity is the volume
information for each MIDI note. So with
that I can just select a given note and
move that up or down to change the
volume.
Pitch bend and modulation are continuous
controls for the whole MIDI track. They
let you dial in extra performance detail
to your MIDI clips. So, I can draw in
pitch and modulation curves here, which
will affect the overall sound over time.
Okay, so that wraps up our MIDI in
Studio 2.0 deep dive. Let us know in the
comments what your favorite things about
Studio [music] 2.0 have been so far.
Thanks for joining us, and we'll see you
next time.
>> Pocket full of keys, pocket full of
keys, pocket [music] full of keys, one
for every place feels like me. Pocket
full of keys, pocket full of keys,
pocket full of keys, one for every place
feels like me. Pocket full of keys,
pocket full of keys, pocket full of
keys, one for every place feels like me.
Pocket full of keys, pocket full of
keys, pocket full of keys, one for every
place feels like
>> [music]